Oliver Tambo Papers 2000.0144
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
- Series A: Personal Documents, 1960-1993
  - Subseries A14: Organisations/Forums/Institutions (Correspondence), 1960-1992 (Box A14)
    - 1991-1992 (23 items) (Box A14., Folder 15)
      Correspondents include: The African-American Institute ( Frank E. Ferrari); Anti-Apartheid Movement (UK) British Defence and Aid Fund for Southern Africa (Director: Ethel de Keyser); First City Bancorporation of Texas; International Defence and Aid Fund for Southern Africa; South African Council of Churches ( Frank Chikane); SANSCO/ NUSAS; Transkei National Library. Subjects include: need for a Commercial bank owned and managed by the majority of the peoples of South Africa; sponsorship of a South African child by the G.M.B. Trade Union; continuation of The BDAF Council/closure of IDAF; SANSCO's response on hearing that a honourary doctorship be awarded to Oliver Tambo by the University of Durban Westville; message from Oliver Tambo on the role of Focus on Political Repression (and IDAF publication) - (See also: Media); request by The Transkei National Library for Oliver Tambo's speeches; invitation to address the Launching Congress of a non-racial students organisation in South Africa; desire of The African-American Institute to strengthen their work in South and Southern Africa; Oliver Tambo's election as National Chairman of the ANC.
  - Subseries A15: Media (Correspondence), 1962-1991
    - Broadcasting (Box A15., Folder 1)
      - Interviews (8 items), 1962, 1985-1989 (Box A15., Folder 1.1)
        Correspondents include: ABC News; BBC Television Centre (including the "Wogan" Programme; Channel Four: After Dark; CBS News ( David Lowe); NOVIB ( Dutch Organisation for International Development Co-operation.
      - Proposals/Suggestions: Documentaries; Television News Programmes (5 items), 1987, 1991 (Box A15., Folder 1.2)
        Correspondents include: Beverley Marcus; Edgard Pisani; Dayle E.Powell (Fellow for Conflict Resolution - The Carter Centre of Emery University).
    - Print (Box A15., Folder 2)
      - Enclosed copies of interviews with Oliver Tambo/other references to Oliver Tambo in the press (5 items), 1981, 1985-1987 (Box A15., Folder 2.1)
        See also: Interview Transcripts. Correspondents include: Monroe Gilmour (article published in The Asheville Citizen); Chandran Nair (article published in New Straits Times); Margaret A. Novicki ( Africa Report).
      - Frontline: Denis Beckett (8 items), 1985-1986 (Box A15., Folder 2.2)
      - Requests: Contributing articles by Oliver Tambo on various subjects (3 items), 1986, 1989 (Box A15., Folder 2.3)
        Correspondents include: Barricada Internacional (overseas publication of the Sandinista National Liberation Front); Sunday Times, Johannesburg.
      - Requests: Information/Interviews with Oliver Tambo/ Nelson Mandela (20 items), 1973, 1981, 1984, 1986-1991 (Box A15., Folder 2.4)
        Correspondents include: Jeremy Brooks; Joe Davidson ( Wall Street Journal); Earl W. Foell ( Christian Science Monitor); Leadership; Playboy; Scope; Sunday Times of Zambia ( Robinson Makayi); Stanley Uys.
  - Subseries A16: Publishers/Publications, 1978-1991 (Box A16)
    - Correspondence (Box A16., Folder 1)
      - General (3 items), undated, 1991 (Box A16., Folder 1.1)
      - Autobiography/Biography: Ben Turok - Oliver Tambo Speaks (2 items), 1985, 1987 (Box A16., Folder 1.2)
        Includes Ben Turok and Adelaide Tambo correspondence.
      - Autobiography/Biography (General re: Oliver Tambo, 4 items), 1986, 1989 (Box A16., Folder 1.3)
        Correspondents include: John Battersby; Antony Harwood ( Aitken and Stone).
      - Other Publications: (Book of Southern African liberation movement documents; Preparing for Power, 4 items), 1982, 1987 (Box A16., Folder 1.4)
        Correspondents: Immanuel Wallerstein; Deidre Mullane
      - Requests: Permission to include essays/letters in various publications (8 items), 1986, 1988, 1990-1991 (Box A16., Folder 1.5)
        Correspondents include: Dr. Lewis Baldwin; Valerie Aubry ( Oxford University Press).
      - Requests/Responses directed to Oliver Tambo re forwards etc for inclusion in respective publications (11 items - includes 1 photograph), 1986, 1989, 1990 (Box A16., Folder 1.6)
        Correspondents: Anthony Heard; Esther Levitan; Diana E.H.Russell.
      - Requests directed to Oliver Tambo re information for purposes of publication on: Trevor Huddleston; Nelson Mandela; Albert Luthuli (7 items), undated, 1986, 1988-1990 (Box A16., Folder 1.7)
        Correspondents include: Mary Benson; Deborah D. Honoré; ( Oxford University Press); William Borman
    - Interview Transcripts (Published/unpublished form, 12 items), 1978, 1983-1990 (Box A16., Folder 2)
      Items include:Tambo Denounces Western Intervention, Algiers ( Revolution Africaine)/Original in French, May 1978; Interview for the FRG Daily, Die Neue, October 1978; Republication of original interview between Tony Heard and Oliver Tambo in Cape Times, 1985; Meeting between Comrade Honecker and Oliver Tambo, Berlin, 15 August 1986; Report: Salient points from Oliver Tambo's response to questions raised by Cuban Ambassador to Luanda, 5 March 1989.
      - Autobiographical Notes made on Audio Cassettes: Transcripts: (9 items), undated (Box A16., Folder 2.1)
      - Interview Transcripts with Adelaide Tambo (2 items), undated
        Items include: Interview with Ben Turok. 15p. Ts.
    - Manuscripts (Box A16., Folder 3)
      - The Struggle for South Africa: A Reference Guide to Movements, Organisations and Institutions. Centre of African Studies - Eduardo Mondlane University, Maputo, 1983. (Box A16., Folder 3.1)
        - Introduction and Chapter 1: Setting the Scene (Box A16., Folder 3.1.1)
        - Chapter 2: The Capitalist Ruling Class: Major Forces and Economic Organisations. (Box A16., Folder 3.1.2)
        - Chapter 3: Political Organizations of the Ruling Class and its Allies. (Box A16., Folder 3.1.3)
        - Chapter 4: State Structures and Policies (Box A16., Folder 3.1.4)
        - Chapter 5: Organizations of Classes allied to the Capitalist Ruling Class (Box A16., Folder 3.1.5)
        - Chapter 6: Political Organizations of the National Liberation Movement (Box A16., Folder 3.1.6)
        - Chapter 7: Democratic Trade Unions (Box A16., Folder 3.1.7)
        - Chapter 8: Community, Women's, Students' and other Popular Organizations (Box A16., Folder 3.1.8)
        - Chapter 9: The Democratic White Opposition to Apartheid (Box A16., Folder 3.1.9)
        - Chapter 10: Other Political and Miscellaneous Organizations (Box A16., Folder 3.1.10)
      - A History of the ANC - F. Meli, undated (Box A16., Folder 3.2)
        - Introduction and Chapter 1: Early Wars of Resistance (Box A16., Folder 3.2.1)
        - Chapter 2: Sources of Inspiration, 1900 - 1912 (Box A16., Folder 3.2.2)
        - Chapter 3: The Formation of the ANC (Box A16., Folder 3.2.3)
        - Chapter 4: The ANC and Workers’ Organizations (Box A16., Folder 3.2.4)
        - Fundamental Changes, 1930 - 1949 (Box A16., Folder 3.2.5)
        - Chapter 6: Defiance and New Strategies, 1949 - 1960 (Box A16., Folder 3.2.6)
        - Armed Resistance and Mass Mobilisation, 1961-1969 (Box A16., Folder 3.2.7)
        - Chapter 8: Re-Emergence of the ANC, 1969-1985 (Box A16., Folder 3.2.8)
        - Footnotes (Box A16., Folder 3.2.9)
      - Oliver Tambo Speaks by Ben Turok (Manuscript incomplete) (Box A16., Folder 3.3)
      - Outline of a book on MK ( 10 Years of Armed Struggle), 1987 (Box A16., Folder 3.4)
      - Cape of Storms by Anthony Heard (Only Chapter 15, Addressed to Adelaide Tambo), 1990 July 10 (Box A16., Folder 3.5)
      - Unknown Manuscript (Includes extracts taken from Sechaba), 1970-1971 (Box A16., Folder 3.6)
  - Speeches and Statements
    Includes drafted and completed speeches and statements.
      - 1969-1973 (Box A17., Folder 1.1)
        - The Present Stage of the Struggle against Apartheid in South Africa, 1968
        - Miscellaneous draft. (May be related to previous address) 3p. Ms., circa 1968
        - Apartheid - A Threat to Africa's Survival: Unit on Apartheid, Department of Political & Security Council Affairs, United Nations. 11p. Ts., 1971 May
        - Statement to the UN Special Committee on the Policies of Apartheid of the Republic of South Africa, Stockholm. 14p. Ts., 1968 June 17
        - Presidential Address (Morogoro Conference). 17p. Ms., 1969
        - A Call to Freedom. 5p. Ms., 1971 December 16
        - Address (London). 12p. Ts., 1972 June 26
        - Address to the Political Committee of the International Conference in Support of the Victims of Colonialism and Apartheid in Southern Africa, (Oslo). 7p. Ts., 1973 April 11
      - 1975-1980 (Box A17., Folder 1.2)
        - Message on the Occasion of 20th Anniversary of the Tanganyika African National Union ( TANU), 3p. Ts., circa 1975
        - Statement to the 9th Extraordinary Session of the Council of Foreign Ministers of the Organisation of African Unity, Dar Es Salaam, 7p. Ts., 1975 April 7 - 10
        - New Year Message: Master Draft. 4p. Ts., 1978
        - Draft Statement to the National Conference of Solidarity for the Independence and Sovereignty of the Peoples of Southern Africa Against Colonialism, Racism and Apartheid, ( Reggio Emilia, Italy). 9p. Ts., 1978 November 25
        - New Year Message on the Occasion of the 67th Anniversary of the ANC. 6p. Ts., 1979 January
        - Message to the People of South Africa on the occasion of the 68th Anniversary of the ANC. Ts., 1980 January 8
        - Forward to a People's Government.
      - 1981 (Box A17., Folder 1.3)
        - South Africa: Imperialist Strategy and the Struggle against Imperialism: Institute of Marxist Studies.
        - An Interview with Comrade Oliver Tambo - Radio Freedom. 15p. Ts., circa 1980
        - Statement. 22p. Ts., 1981 January 8
        - Address to the International Conference on Sanctions against South Africa, Paris. 16p. Ts., 1981 May 21
        - Statement on the Occasion of the 60th Anniversary of the South African Communist Party. 12p. Ts., 1981 July 30
        - Statement on the Death Sentence passed on three ANC and MK Militants, Broadcast on Radio Freedom, Luanda. 2p. Ts., 1981 August 20
        - Statement at the First Conference - Women's Section ANC (SA), Luanda. Ts., 1981 September 10
        - Statement to the Luanda Afro-Arab Conference. 7p. Ts., 1981 December 6 - 9
      - 1982 (Box A17., Folder 1.4)
        - Europe and the Solution for Peace in Southern Africa [Draft]. 8p. Ts.
        - Statement at a Mass Rally, Bairro De Leberdade, Maputo. 16p. Ts., 1982 February 14
        - Miscellaneous draft - Year of Unity in Action. 7p. Ts., 1982 March 12
        - Draft speech for OAU Summit. (2 versions). 13p. 10p. Ts., 9p Ms., 1982 November
        - Statement to the UN General Assembly on the Question of Apartheid, New York. [Draft]. 7p. Ts., 1982 November
        - Statement at the Special Session of the UN General Assembly summoned to confer UN Awards to Distinguished Representatives of the World Anti-Apartheid Movement. [Draft]. 3p. Ts., 1982 November 5
        - Statement to the Council on Foreign Relations: The African National Congress, the United States and the future of South Africa. [Draft]. 9p. Ts., 1982 November 8
        - Message condemning attack against Lesotho by SADF, 1982 December 13
      - 1983 (Box A17., Folder 1.5)
        - Draft - Answers for Avant-garde Interview
        - Draft - preparatory notes to use for the OAU Liberation Committee. 13p. Ts., 1983 January 14
        - Draft Statement to the OAU Liberation Committee: Arusha, Tanzania. 10p. Ts., 1983 February 10
        - Ibid. 11p. Ts.
        - Draft Statement at the Summit of the Non-Aligned Movement, New Delhi. 15p. Ts., 1983 March 7 - 11
        - Speech to the Non-Aligned Summit of Heads of State and Government, New Delhi. 7p. Ts., 1983 March 7 - 11
        - Opening Speech by Oliver Tambo to The First Conference of the Department of Information and Publicity, Lusaka, 1983 July 5 - 9
        - Statement of Acceptance by Oliver Tambo, on the Occasion of the Presentation to Nelson Mandela of the Simon Bolivar Prize, Caracas. 16p. Ts., 1983 July 24
      - 1984 (Box A17., Folder 1.6)
        - Draft Speech re "complex and explosive situation" in Southern Africa (Not delivered). 9p. Ts., circa 1984
        - Statement of the National Executive Committee, delivered by President Oliver Tambo. 19p. Ts. (Duplicate. See also: NEC - Statements), 1984 January 18
        - Call to the People of South Africa [Draft]. 3p. Ts., 1984 June 16
        - Statement of the ANC to the 42nd Session of the OAU Liberation Committee, Arusha, Tanzania. [Draft]. 10p. Ts., 1984 August 27 - September 1
        - Statement to the OAU Summit Meeting of the Heads of State and Government, Addis Ababa. 8p. Ts., 1984 November 12 - 15
        - Statement to the Press: Addis Ababa, 1984 November 16
      - 1985 (Box A17., Folder 1.7)
        - Statement of the National Executive Committee. 20p. Ts. (Duplicate. See also: National Executive Committee - Statements), 1985 January 8
        - Draft NEC Statement. 17p. Ts., undated
        - Ibid. 15p. Ts.
        - Statement (telex): "To the People of Uitenhage"
        - Address to the 21st Summit of the OAU, Addis Ababa. 7p. Ts., 1985 July 18 - 20
        - Statement to the 12th World Festival of Youth and Students, Moscow. 1p. Ts., 1985 July
        - Draft Statement at the Opening of SOMAFCO. 6p. Ts., 1985 August 22
        - Statement, Chatham House, London. 3p. Ts., 1985 October 29
      - 1986 (Box A17., Folder 1.8)
        - Address to the ILO Conference. [Draft]. 8p. Ts.
        - Message of the National Executive Committee, delivered by Comrade Oliver Tambo. 17p. Ts. (Duplicate. See also: National Executive committee - Statements), 1986 January 8
        - Ibid. [Draft]. 23p. Ts.
        - Ibid. [Draft]. 21p. Ts.
      - Statement at the Funeral of the Late Comrade Moses Mbheki Mabhida Maputo. 5p. Ts., 1986 March 29 (Box A17., Folder 1.8)
        - Address on receiving the degree of Doctor of Laws (Honoris Cause) at Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi. 8p. Ts., 1986 May 9
        - Draft Statement: The role of the Youth in the Struggle for Liberation, Democracy and Development, ANC Youth Week. 7p. Ts. (Includes 2 pages of hand-written notes: Tasks of Youth), 1986 June 9 - 16
        - Address to the 8th Summit of the Non-Aligned Movement, Harare. 8p. Ts., 1986 September 1 - 6
        - Statement of Acceptance of the Ho Chi Minh Award bestowed on the ANC by the World Peace Council, Luanda. 2p. Ts., 1986 December 15
        - Statement of the National Executive Committee delivered by President Oliver Tambo on Heroes Day, on the occasion of the 25th Anniversary of the Formation of Umkhonto we Sizwe, the People's Army. 23p. Ts. (Duplicate. See also: NEC - Statements), 1986 December 16
        - Draft International Appeal on the occasion of the 75th Anniversary of the ANC. Ts. 2p.
      - 1987 (Box A17., Folder 1.9)
        - A Call to the People of South Africa. 6p. Ts., circa 1987
        - Statement of the National Executive Committee on the occasion of the 75th Anniversary of the ANC, presented by President Oliver Tambo. 22p. Ts. (Duplicate. See also National Executive Committee - Statements), 1987 January 8
        - Address at the 75th Anniversary Meeting of the ANC, Lusaka. 5p. Ts., 1987 January 8
        - Draft - General guidelines of activities for marking the 75th Anniversary of the ANC. 2p. Ts.
        - Address before the Foreign Policy Association, New York. 30p. Ts., 1987 January 22
        - May Day Speech, Stockholm. 3p. Ts.
        - Address: Visit to Australia, 1987 March - April
        - Address to The West Australian Council of Churches, 1987 March - April
        - Draft - May Day Speech, Stockholm. 5p. Ms.
        - Keynote Address - People's National Party ( PNP) Founders Day Banquet, Jamaica. 20p. Ts., 1987 July 4
        - Address to Joint Session of Parliament, Trinidad and Tobago. 11p. Ts., 1987 July 10
        - Statement - Venezuela Foreign Minister's Lunch. 4p. Ts., 1987 July 13
        - Speech delivered on behalf of the Liberation Movements at the Opening Session of the 23rd Summit of the OAU. 3p. Ts., 1987 July 27
        - Statement to the International Conference on Children, Repression and the Law in Apartheid South Africa, Harare. 7p. Ts., 1987 September 24 - 27
        - Opening Statement - Special NEC Meeting. 3p. Ms., 1987 October 5 - 8
        - Statement of the Delegation of the ANC to the Informal Meeting of Delegations. 6p. Ms., 1987 November 4 - 5
        - Speech on the occasion of the award of an honorary doctorate to Nelson Mandela by the Karl Marx University of the GDR, Leipzig. 6p. Ts. (Includes transcript of Laudation. 8p.), 1987 November 11
        - Statement at the closing session of the International Conference against Apartheid for a Democratic South Africa, Arusha, Tanzania. 5p. Ts., 1987 December 1 - 4
      - 1988 (Box A17., Folder 1.1)
        - Statement at the Harare Symposium on the Survival and Development of Children in the Frontline States and Southern Africa. 6p. Ts., 1988 March 1 - 5
        - Draft Statement for the above Symposium. Ts. and Ms.
        - Statement at the AWEPAA Conference, Harare, Zimbabwe. 4p. Ts., 1988 March 28
        - Statement at the 50th Session of the OAU Coordinating Committee for the Liberation of Africa, Harare. 15p. Ts., 1988 May 13
        - Draft Statement at the 25th Anniversary OAU Summit Meeting of Heads of State and Government, Addis Ababa. 8p. Ts., 1988 May 25
        - Ibid. 6p. Ts.
        - Ibid. 6p. Ts.
        - Ibid. 5p. Ts. and Ms.
        - Ibid. 4p. Ts.
        - Statement at the War on Want Conference, London: "Peace and Development in the Frontline States." 7p. Ts., 1988 June 9
        - Statement at the Launch of the " Nelson Mandela: Freedom at 70" Campaign, Wembley Stadium, London. 2p. Ts., 1988 June 11
        - Draft Statement at the SADCC Summit Meeting, Maputo. 3p. Ms., 1988 July 15
        - Address delivered to the 10th General Conference of the United National Independence Party, Zambia. 5p. Ts.
        - Statement given on behalf of the Southern African Liberation Movements, at the 7th Summit Meeting of the Preferential Trade Area for Eastern and Southern African States, Arusha. 6p. Ts., 1988 December 1 - 2
        - Ibid. 9p. Ts.
      - 1989 (Box A17., Folder 1.11)
        - Statement at the 19th African-American Conference, Lusaka. 6p. Ts., 1989 January 12
        - Statement at the Socialist International Conference on Southern Africa, Harare. 8p. Ts., 1989 February 15
        - Statement at the Press Conference, Moscow. 3p. Ms., 1989 March 10
        - Message of the President to the 7th Party Congress of the South African Communist Party. 6p. Ts., 1989 April
        - Press Statement in response to the five year plan presented to the National Party Conference by President-elect, F. W. de Klerk. Ts., 1989 June 29
        - Statement at the 25th OAU Assembly of Heads of State and Government, Addis Ababa. 13p. Ts. (Includes handwritten appendix), 1989 July 24 - 26
        - Statement to the Rally to Welcome the Released Leaders, Johannesburg. 8p. Ts., 1989 October 29
        - Statement at the SADCC Summit Meeting, Maputo. (Draft), 1989 July 15
      - 1990 (Box A17., Folder 1.12)
        - Address to a conference organised by Socialist International and its Committee on Southern Africirca [Draft]. 12p. Ts.
        - Draft Statement on behalf of Oliver Tambo re meeting with Nelson Mandela's and others in Sweden. 3p. Ms.
        - Message to the Re-launch of the ANC Women's League, Durban. 3p. Ts., 1990 August 9
        - Draft Statement - Re-launch of the ANC Women's League. 5p. Ts.
        - Ibid. 2p. Ts.
        - Ibid. 1p. Ms.
        - Message to the Re-launching Rally of the ANC Youth League, Johannesburg. 9p. Ts., 1990 October 27
        - Statement - Lusaka Airport. 2p. Ts., 1990 December 7
        - Speech to the National Consultative Conference of the ANC, Johannesburg. 7p. (Incomplete). Ts., 1990 December 16
        - Scheme of the Presidential report to the Conference. 3p. Ts.
        - The Measure of Your Victory - on the 30th Anniversary of the British Anti-Apartheid Movement. 8p. Ts. (Draft)
      - 1991-1992 (Box A17., Folder 1.13)
        - Address to participants at the 10th and Final Conference of the International Defence and Aid Fund for Southern Africa. 10p. Ts.
        - Message to the Extended PNYC of the ANC Youth League. 6p. Ts.
        - Acceptance speech on receiving the honourary Doctor of Law Degree, awarded by UWC (Draft). 9p. Ts.
        - Message to the South African Youth on the Occasion of the 15th Anniversary of June 16th. 3p. Ts.
        - Statement to the ANC National Conference, Johannesburg. 11p. Ts., 1991 June
        - Statement to the ANC National Conference, Durban. 12p. Ts., 1991 July
        - Draft Statement to the Joint Congress to create one united non-racial student organisation. 6p. Ts.
        - Message of condolences from the President and Commander-in-Chief of the ANC re murders of Albert Xhamfu and Edward Charles (OFS).
        - Lecture delivered to Youth and Students of Ghana. 8p. Ts.
        - Message to the People of Ghana. 4p. Ts.
        - Speech delivered whilst presenting the first "Ruth First Memorial Award to Nobel Laureate, Nadine Gordimar, at the University of the Western Cape. 3p. Ts., 1992 August 17
      - Miscellaneous: (22 items), Undated (Box A17., Folder 1.14)
        - Statement on behalf of the South Africa United Front: Oliver Tambo and Vusumzi L Make
        - Address by Oliver Tambo on the occasion of the granting of the Freedom of the City of Kweke to Robert Mugabe and Nelson Mandela
        - Peace and Development in the Frontline States - South Africa's Total Strategy and The Frontline States.
    - Published in the form of pamphlets, journal articles, etc. (Box A17., Folder 2)
      - 1967-1984 (Box A17., Folder 2.1)
        - Message published in Sechaba, 1967 January
        - "A Great Step Forward" - Message published in Sechaba to President Julius Nyerere on the occasion of his announcement of the nationalization of all banks in Tanzania, 1967 March 1967
        - "Capture the Citadel" - A Broadcast to South Africa on the occasion of the 8th Anniversary of the formation of Umkhonto we Sizwe, 1969 December
        - Miscellaneous published article re the Afro-Asian People's Organisation, circa 1970s
        - "Call to Revolution." Apartheid - A Collection of writings on South African Racism by South Africans. edited by Alex La Guma. Laurence and Wishart, 1972
        - "Southern Africa in Struggle" - Speech delivered at a meeting in London to commemorate June 26, South Africa Freedom Day and to condemn the 600-year alliance between Britain and Portugal, published in Sechaba, 1973
        - "The ANC and the Pan Africanist Movement" - Extracts from a statement made by the ANC to the 6th Pan African Congress, Dar es Salaam: published in Sechaba, 1974 October
        - "A Future Free of Exploitation." An address to the First Congress of the MPLA, Luanda, December 1977, published in Sechaba, 1978/2nd quarter
        - Booklet: The Year of the Charter - Message to the People of South Africa on the occasion of the 68th Anniversary of the ANC, 1980 January 8
        - Mr. Oliver Tambo of the African National Congress of South Africa Addresses United Nations Special Committee Against Apartheid - New York. Published by the United Nations Centre against Apartheid, 1981 June 11
        - " O.R. Tambo - The Spirit of June 26." published in Sechaba, 1981 July